Guide to the Leo Holub Photographs of Stanford University
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Leo Holub photographs of Stanford University
1946-1992
PC0138
Holub, Leo, 1916-2010
12 Linear feet
Collection contains prints (mostly black and white) of Stanford presidents, faculty, trustees, staff, students on campus, campus lands, and construction, as well as a series of mounted images from Stanford Seen, an exhibition of Holub’s photographs held in 1964. Other topics include a sit-in at Dr. Sterling’s office 1966; photos of Prof. Moffatt Hancock and prints Holub made of Hancock’s negatives of campus scenes; images of Chris Stinehour, stone carver working on the Quad; and prints Holub made from glass plate negatives of historic images of Stanford. Collection also includes prints of images used in the book LEO HOLUB PHOTOGRAPHER, which documents his whole career.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Leo Holub, graphic artist and photographer, studied at the Art Institute of Chicago and the California School of Fine Arts, most notably under Ansel Adams. He came to Stanford in 1960, working first in the Planning Department and then in 1969 creating the photography program in the department of art, at the invitation of Lorenz Eitner, head of the department. Holub taught for 11 years, retiring as senior lecturer of photography, emeritus, in 1980.
Description of the Collection
Collection contains prints (mostly black and white) of Stanford presidents, faculty, trustees, staff, students on campus, campus lands, and construction, as well as a series of mounted images from Stanford Seen, an exhibition of Holub’s photographs held in 1964. Other topics include a sit-in at Dr. Sterling’s office 1966; photos of Prof. Moffatt Hancock and prints Holub made of Hancock’s negatives of campus scenes; images of Chris Stinehour, stone carver working on the Quad; and prints Holub made from glass plate negatives of historic images of Stanford. Collection also includes prints of images used in the book LEO HOLUB PHOTOGRAPHER, which documents his whole career.
Access Terms
Hancock, Moffatt.; Holub, Leo, 1916-2010; Sterling, J. E. Wallace, (John Ewart Wallace), 1906-1985; Stinehour, Chris.; Photoprints.
Collection Contents
- Photographs, Accession ARCH-2009-189
  - 8x10 b/w prints
    - Russian Posters, WWI Posters (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rare Books and Manuscripts (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - More Imprint related images [rare books and documents, people at events] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - letter from Frank J. Novak re suspension of Imprint, 1988; and copies of correspondence between Ansel Adams and Robert Hind (development office) re a Stanford photo project 1960-61 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      seems to be the one done for PACE, contact sheets of which are in the Stanford Historic Photograph Collection, GP boxes 50-51
    - Sit-in, Dr. Sterling's office, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - Dr. Sterling's retirement, Fairmont Hotel, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Stanford Portraits (Box 1, Folder 9)
      includes Paul Ehrlich, Al Hastorf, Prof. Ponge, Mrs. Packard, John Gardner, Janet Winters, Paul Hanna, Prof. Dreckmeier, Gunther Nagel, Edith Mirrielees
    - Faculty, Board Members (Box 1, Folder 10)
      includes George Bach, Arthur Kornberg, Wally Sterling, Thomas Church, Ralph Heintz, Dick Lyman, Gerald Gunther, Carl Spaeth, Albert Hastorf, Donald Kennedy, Albert Guerard, Lincoln Moses, Prof. Porterfield, James Gibbs, Donald Kennedy, Fred Hargadon, Herb Packer. Also an Engineering Design classroom scene, Pitzer's installation.
    - Prints from Prof. Wells negatives [SU historic images from glass plate negatives] (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Hopkins Marine Station (Box 1)
      some are copies of historic images and documents
  - Prints 11x14 and some smaller:
    - Leo Holub photos of Prof. Moffatt Hancock (8x10) and prints Leo made of Hancock's negatives (11x14 – campus scenes) [blue box] (Box 2)
    - [unlabeled Kodak box black and yellow containing miscellaneous images] (Box 2)
    - Beckman [or Bauman?] Luncheon award at Hoover House [blue box] (Box 2)
    - Portfolio for Warren Christopher (Trustee) [orange box: one image of Christopher, rest are campus scenes] (Box 2)
    - Chris Stinehour, stone carver working on the Quad [blue box] (Box 2)
    - Stanford Historical [red box: old images copied or printed by Leo]
  - Prints, mostly 11x14 inches, in folders:
    - Early views the Farm [1950s] includes many construction scenes (Box 3)
    - Hoover [Tower and views from] (Box 3)
    - Lake Lagunita [views of campus across the lake] (Box 3)
    - SLAC [construction] (Box 3)
    - Buildings (Box 3)
    - Stanford land (Box 3)
    - Professors (Box 4)
    - Nobel faculty (Box 4)
      Linus Pauling, Arthur Schawlow, Arthur Kornberg, Paul Flory, Robert Hofstadter, George Bach, Burton Richter, Felix Bloch, Milton Friedman
    - Lawrence Crawley; unidentified; Nan Keohane (Box 4)
    - Faculty: general (Box 4)
    - Staff (Box 4)
    - Hanna House and Paul Hanna (Box 4)
    - Presidents [Sterling, Lyman, Kennedy, Casper] (Box 4)
  - Mounted images from Stanford Seen Exhibition, 1964
    - "Captain Midnight" observing foot/bike traffic, Hoover Tower and 1 Hoover office, Registration Day. (Box 5)
    - construction scenes, images from the day Pres. Kennedy was shot, Tresidder Union (exterior and interior mostly with people). (Box 6)
    - Quad images (exterior), mostly with people; assorted building interiors with people. (Box 7)
    - Images of Stanford lands (sometimes with people) such as Lake Lagunita, Jasper Ridge, horse barns, roads, and the Mausoleum. Also 1 image of the Memorial Tablet (to Leland Stanford Jr.) and 1 image of the SU manhole cover. (Box 8)
    - Images of people outside various campus buildings. (Box 9)
    - Includes Registration Day, Tresidder Union, the Claw and Bookstore, Hoover Tower, and others. (Box 11)
  - Unmounted images from Stanford Seen, and a copy of the book Stanford Seen (Box 10)
  - Assorted unmounted images
    - Research Park (Box 11)
    - Lab in Old Chemistry (Box 11)
    - View of San Francisco from Red Rock Hill (Box 11)
    - Mary Sunseri teaching calculus (Box 11)
  - Envelope of posters of Holub exhibits or images (Box 11)
  - LEO HOLUB PHOTOGRAPHER: list of image captions, note re missing prints, and assorted images (Box 12)
  - Prints (11x14 inch) of images used in LEO HOLUB PHOTOGRAPHER #1-125 (Box 12)
  - LEO HOLUB PHOTOGRAPHER (Box 12)
  - Framed image: Phoebe H. Brown at home in San Francisco with Mr. James Tong Lee, 1978 [image no. 41 from LEO HOLUB PHOTOGRAPHER]